<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text"></title>
<subtitle type="text"></subtitle>
<generator uri="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://seanoliver.me/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://seanoliver.me" />
<updated>2014-03-09T15:58:17-07:00</updated>
<id>http://seanoliver.me/</id>
<author>
  <name></name>
  <uri>http://seanoliver.me/</uri>
  <email></email>
</author>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[4 Ways to Be More Productive While Driving]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://seanoliver.me/driving-productively" />
  <id>http://seanoliver.me/driving-productively</id>
  <published>2014-01-02T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  <updated>2014-01-02T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://seanoliver.me</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;According to the Federal Highway Administration, &lt;a href=&quot;http://bigstory.ap.org/article/stats-show-americans-not-driving-anymore&quot;&gt;Americans are no longer driving as much as they once were&lt;/a&gt;. Owning a car is expensive, young people are opting to live in cities with public transit, and technology continues to reduce the need for meetings &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=IRL&quot;&gt;IRL&lt;/a&gt;. However that doesn&amp;#39;t change the fact that we&amp;#39;re still a car culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Driving continues to be the primary way most Americans get from A to B. During this holiday seasona alone, I spent time visitng friends and family all around the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mid-Atlantic_states&quot;&gt;Mid-Atlantic&lt;/a&gt; to places like Philadelphia, New York, Annapolis, and Binghamton (to name a few). In fact when all is said and done, I spent a total of &lt;em&gt;24 hours and 8 minutes&lt;/em&gt; driving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;4 Driving Productivity Tips&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s a lot of time spent looking ahead and trying to stay awake, but until &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Autonomous_car&quot;&gt;cars start driving themselves&lt;/a&gt;, it seems like all we can do is stare at break lights and slam some Starbucks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are four things I do to be significantly more productive behind the wheel:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://audible.com/&quot;&gt;Audible&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; I love reading a good book, but I seldom make the time to do so with everything else I&amp;#39;ve got going on day-to-day. Audible (an &lt;a href=&quot;http://amazon.com&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; company) lets you pick from a huge library of audio books and listen to them across all of your devices. Audible&amp;#39;s app also allows you to listen to books at 2x speed and offers a quick &amp;quot;jump back 15 seconds&amp;quot; button, in case you miss anything---these are common features in lots of audio book apps, including &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewGrouping?cc=us&amp;amp;id=28&quot;&gt;iTunes Audiobooks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://umanoapp.com/&quot;&gt;Umano&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; I read blogs to keep up on news, but scanning TechCrunch while driving is about as good an idea as texting while driving. This is where Umano comes in. Umano selects the top news stories from popular blogs and hires professional voice actors to read them. Once you&amp;#39;re done listening to a story, the app will begin reading the next one in the feed. This makes it easy to keep your hands and eyes where they should be while you&amp;#39;re driving. I love listening to Umano. It&amp;#39;s as enjoyable as listening to &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NPR&quot;&gt;NPR&lt;/a&gt;. It turns mind-numbing idle time into opportunities to get smarter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;iOS Speak Selection.&lt;/strong&gt; This isn&amp;#39;t an app, but it&amp;#39;s an invaluable tool for turning all of the other types of written content you may encounter into auditory goodness. If you have an iOS device, enable Speak Selection by going to Settings &amp;gt; General &amp;gt; Accessibility &amp;gt; Speak Selection &amp;gt; On. Now when you highlight any text on your phone, you&amp;#39;ll see a &amp;quot;Speak&amp;quot; option, which reads aloud whatever content you selected. Here are some popular use cases I&amp;#39;ve encountered:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reading &lt;em&gt;Wikipedia articles&lt;/em&gt; aloud to settle arguments with other passengers in the car&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reading &lt;em&gt;Yelp reviews&lt;/em&gt; aloud to decide where to go to dinner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reading &lt;em&gt;movie showtimes&lt;/em&gt; aloud to figure out which one you can make&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reading &lt;em&gt;text messages&lt;/em&gt; aloud to determine if they&amp;#39;re worth having a passenger &amp;#39;ghost write&amp;#39; a response for you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Language Learning Podcasts.&lt;/strong&gt; I&amp;#39;ve been &lt;a href=&quot;/learning-chinese&quot;&gt;learning Chinese&lt;/a&gt; for the last 2.5 years. There are a lot of useful and entertaining Podcasts out there, but I&amp;#39;ve found the ones focused language learning have been most rewarding. Podcasts are great for language learning because (1) they&amp;#39;re short, and (2) it&amp;#39;s easy to replay certain sections until you get it. Plus, the editorial nature of Podcasts helps immerse you in a target language and expose you to the culture of the associated country. For those of you learning Chinese, I highly recommend &lt;a href=&quot;http://popupchinese.com/&quot;&gt;Popup Chinese&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://chinesepod.com/&quot;&gt;ChinesePod&lt;/a&gt;. You can also search &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewGrouping?cc=us&amp;amp;id=33&quot;&gt;iTunes&amp;#39; Podcast Library&lt;/a&gt; for your language of choice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Drive Safely&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, it&amp;#39;s important to find a driving work flow that works for you and your situation in the car. There are times when you need to give even more attention to the road (e.g. city driving) and there&amp;#39;s always the chance an accident will happen that will demand your split-second reaction times. This might seem obvious, but keep the following in mind:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set up your device (e.g. phone, iPad, etc.) with the content you want to listen to before you start driving.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set up your car to play the content using USB, Bluetooth, or auxilary audio before you start driving. (Don&amp;#39;t listen through ear buds.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find a volume level and reading speed that allows you to focus but doesn&amp;#39;t take away from your ability to react to situations on the road.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Listen when you&amp;#39;re commuting and/or on a highway. Don&amp;#39;t listen when you&amp;#39;re learning a new route or in a city environment where you have pedestrians and unexpected traffic patterns to contend with.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will soon come a time when &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Google_driverless_car&quot;&gt;cars won&amp;#39;t need humans to drive them&lt;/a&gt;, but until then, it&amp;#39;s time we started listening.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://seanoliver.me/driving-productively&quot;&gt;4 Ways to Be More Productive While Driving&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;http://seanoliver.me&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on January 02, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Be More Productive with the "Do" Folder]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://seanoliver.me/do-folder" />
  <id>http://seanoliver.me/do-folder</id>
  <published>2013-12-22T00:00:00-08:00</published>
  <updated>2013-12-22T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://seanoliver.me</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Modern tech workers have more things to do than time to do them. Requests come from every direction, and tasks pile up quickly if you&amp;#39;re not always trying to stay on top of it. I&amp;#39;ve tried a variety of GTD and task management workflows over the years, but none of them stuck. Each method took so much time to manage that it took away from time I could be spending getting things done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over time I borrowed aspects of other GTD systems and hobbled together a method that&amp;#39;s worked for me. It&amp;#39;s called the Do folder:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/do-folder.png&quot; alt=&quot;My Do Folder&quot;&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What is the Do folder?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a given day I get inbound tasks from email, meetings, phone calls, texts, and so on. Keeping track of everything that has to be done takes time, and that&amp;#39;s where most productivity workflows tend to fall down. Over time, I&amp;#39;ve started to do a good job at keeping track of things in apps. I use a lot of apps to get things done, and each one has it&amp;#39;s own purpose. The Do folder is where I keep all those apps, all the apps I need to take action on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What do you put in it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Do folder won&amp;#39;t work if you don&amp;#39;t use it. This is why it&amp;#39;s important to keep a few key &amp;quot;anchor apps&amp;quot; inside. Anchor apps are apps that you&amp;#39;ll always use no matter what, because you have to (e.g. Mail and Calendar). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then you add other apps that you &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to use. There are a lot of great apps out there that can keep you productive if you use them, but using them daily means you need to turn them into habits, and that&amp;#39;s hard. Adding these apps in the Do folder with your other Anchor apps ensures you&amp;#39;ll see them and reminds you to open them. It&amp;#39;s a kind of &lt;strong&gt;halo effect&lt;/strong&gt;, so I call them &amp;quot;Halo apps.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;My Anchor Apps&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mailbox.&lt;/strong&gt; For keeping track of the email that actually needs action taken on it. As I&amp;#39;ve written before, &lt;a href=&quot;/email-notifications&quot;&gt;I don&amp;#39;t use push notifications for email&lt;/a&gt; but Mailbox does have a useful badge notification setting I use. It shows the total count of emails in your inbox, rather than unread email only. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Any.DO.&lt;/strong&gt; This is my to do list of choice for keeping a handle on everything that needs to get done that does not come in via email. I use &lt;a href=&quot;http://lifehacker.com/5985481/anydo-moment-offers-a-quick-simple-overview-of-your-daily-to+dos&quot;&gt;Any.DO Moment&lt;/a&gt; every morning to prioritize my tasks for the day. The badge counter only shows the tasks I need to complete for that day, so when the folder is closed, the folder&amp;#39;s badge number shows the sum of Mailbox and Any.DO---an overall count of what needs to get done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Calendar.&lt;/strong&gt; I still prefer Apple&amp;#39;s default Calendar app, but their badge notifications are usually innacurate, so I turn them off entirely. Calendar is important enough to my day that I don&amp;#39;t need a notification to get me into it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;My Halo Apps&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MyFitnessPal.&lt;/strong&gt; I use it every day to keep track of my diet and exercise and make sure that I&amp;#39;m generally improving my fitness. It&amp;#39;s part of a daily personal fitness committment I&amp;#39;ve made to myself, which is why it made the cut for the Do folder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lift.&lt;/strong&gt; I use Lift to keep myself accountable for the various repeatable tasks that I want to do every day and turn into habits. I&amp;#39;ve had the app for a while, but only when I put it in the Do folder did I make it a daily habit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evernote.&lt;/strong&gt; My Evernote workflow is constantly evolving. I use an &amp;#39;Inbox&amp;#39; note (a la David Allen) to keep track of everything I need to organize later---things like book recommendations, notes to go into Any.DO tasks, and ideas for side projects or startup companies. Keeping it here makes sure I keep it top of mind and reorganize it when necessary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone&amp;#39;s different in how they get things done, so maybe this exact implementation won&amp;#39;t work for you. That&amp;#39;s fine. Maybe part of it will. At the end of the day being productive is about what you &lt;em&gt;produce&lt;/em&gt;. The important thing is not to overthink it and commit to the things that work.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://seanoliver.me/do-folder&quot;&gt;Be More Productive with the "Do" Folder&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;http://seanoliver.me&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on December 22, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why to Try]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://seanoliver.me/why-to-try" />
  <id>http://seanoliver.me/why-to-try</id>
  <published>2013-10-17T00:00:00-07:00</published>
  <updated>2013-10-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://seanoliver.me</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;No. Try not. Do... or do not. There is no try.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;footer&gt;Yoda in &lt;cite title=&#39;The Empire Strikes Back&#39; year=&#39;1980&#39;&gt;The Empire Strikes Back, 1980&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yoda’s immortal words reflect a flawed situation in American society: We’ve stopped trying. We’ve stopped trying, and instead, we’ve started doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve started doing because doing implies finishing and—more importantly—succeeding. Trying, on the other hand, means that you’re struggling. It indicates you could fail at any moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask yourself these questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Would you catch a ride with a friend who tries to drive?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Would you hire someone who tries to work?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Would you agree to surgery from a doctor who tries to operate? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably not. Why would you? After all, if you’re trying, you’re struggling. And if you’re struggling, you’re probably about to fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this line of thinking overlooks this simple fact: &lt;em&gt;Everyone must try before they can do.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trying is how we learn. It’s how we explore. It’s how we improve. It’s how we discover things about ourselves and about the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, ask yourself these questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What would the world look like if Leonardo da Vinci never tried to paint? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where would we be if Steve Jobs never tried to sell a computer? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What if Martin Luther King, Jr. never tried to raise his voice? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For each of these people, there was a period during which they needed to try before they could start doing. However in today’s overly critical society, it can be hard to find the motivation to try, to pursue new interests, and to go after big ideas (or small ones).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if you don’t try, you won’t do. And if you don’t do, you won’t succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So try.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://seanoliver.me/why-to-try&quot;&gt;Why to Try&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;http://seanoliver.me&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on October 17, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Turn off Email Notifications]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://seanoliver.me/email-notifications" />
  <id>http://seanoliver.me/email-notifications</id>
  <published>2013-04-29T00:00:00-07:00</published>
  <updated>2013-04-29T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://seanoliver.me</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;About a month ago, I decided to try an experiment and turn off email notifications on my phone and my laptop. I’d read a lot online about the benefits of turning off email notifications, but I was always afraid to try it for fear of missing something important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But after a month of this, I can safely say I’m not going back. My stress level has decreased, and my ability to focus has never been better. I have a greater appreciation for the world around me, and my general happiness level has hugely improved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Notifications make everything seem urgent&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notifications do everything they can to get your attention. They appear, they flash, they vibrate, they chime. They don’t let you ignore them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is really useful when they information they carry is urgent. But it usually isn’t:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Urgent:&lt;/strong&gt; A close friend was bitten by a poisonous snake and only has minutes to live. You alone possess the antidote.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Not Urgent:&lt;/strong&gt; A coworker needs to know why we’re seeing a WoW decline in DAU.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an extreme example, but the point is very few things require an immediate reply. After turning off notifications, I find myself setting aside time to look at email when it’s convenient for me. Then I can prioritize my replies relative to all of the unread emails in my inbox, rather than processing each one as it comes in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Notifications make you less effective&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter how you look at it, the point of a notification is to get you to pay attention to something other than what you’re doing. But there are lots of times, when you need constant, unbroken attention to get something done effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a generic experience I’d often have before turning off notifications:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Begin working on project that requires focus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Receive email notification.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Glance at it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open the email and skim it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider how long it will take to respond and how urgent it is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decide it’s not worth a response right now.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flag it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remind myself what I was doing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get back to work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole process happens in a few seconds, so it doesn’t feel like a huge tax. But in reality, it breaks up your thought process, causing you to make mistakes and ultimately increasing the amount of time it takes to get the task done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Notifications consume your attention&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many times has this happened to you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You’re walking down the hallway.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You receive an email notification.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You pull out your phone and read the email, while walking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You you arrive at your destination.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You put your phone away.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was going on around you between when you started walking and when you arrived at your destination? Hard to say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a few days without notifications, I noticed how much more often I was bumping into people and having quick conversations. I realized that some of the walls of my office building were painted blue and others white. I noticed there were cherry blossom trees in the courtyard outside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without notifications, I’m getting a lot more out of my days. I have more control over my time, and I finish the things I start more quickly. I’m learning more about the people I work with, and I pay more attention to the world around me.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://seanoliver.me/email-notifications&quot;&gt;Turn off Email Notifications&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;http://seanoliver.me&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on April 29, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Apple's New Ads Look Like Microsoft Made Them]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://seanoliver.me/apple-ads" />
  <id>http://seanoliver.me/apple-ads</id>
  <published>2012-07-30T00:00:00-07:00</published>
  <updated>2012-07-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://seanoliver.me</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;iframe width=&quot;620&quot; height=&quot;349&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/CMcrw8WTWSs&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to admit that I agree with the cacophony of criticism about Apple’s latest round of TV ads. In fact, I almost had an allergic reaction to them when I first saw them air during the Olympics opening ceremony on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They looked and felt like ads that my former employer, Microsoft, used to release in attempt to position themselves as being relevant. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So many issues abound:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;They don’t show the product.&lt;/strong&gt; This is a product ad, not a brand ad or a perception ad. And Apple has always impressed me by the way that they have (almost) always made the product the star of their product ads. Consumers need to see what’s being advertised in order to understand the messaging in a tangible way. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;They don’t explain the product.&lt;/strong&gt; Apple doesn’t always show the product in its ads. A great example of this is the Mac vs. PC campaign that ran through the first half of the 2000s. But that campaign still made the product the star by focusing on each ad on a discrete feature or set of related features, and explaining how they work. That’s something that this campaign utterly fails at doing. In the ad above, the Genius asks the shopper, “It came loaded with all the great apps like iMovie, iPhoto, Garageband… Not ringing a bell?&amp;quot; The consumer at whom this ad is targeted doesn’t know what these apps are. As a result, he doesn’t know why he should care that he doesn’t have them. And if the ad doesn’t tell him that, he’s just going to hear marketing noise and tune out.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;They make the target audience feel stupid.&lt;/strong&gt; This is Apple’s first real effort going after a less tech-savvy group of computer buyers, and this ad makes it clear that they really don’t know how to talk to them at all. The people in this segment are not idiots, in fact, a lot of them are doctors, lawyers, teachers, and otherwise very smart people.They just don’t think about the latest technology all that much, and this ad basically calls them stupid for not buying a Mac. When consumers buy PCs, they are usually doing it after lots of research — after all, it’s a big purchase for most people — and this ad is essentially telling them they made the wrong decision despite all the thought they put into making what they thought was the right one.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;They make the Geniuses look like unsupportive know-it-alls.&lt;/strong&gt; In a similar vein, the Apple Genius in this ad comes off as a true embodiment of the elitist stereotype many have attributed to Apple’s core customer. When Apple first introduced the Geniuses, they worked because they weren’t that stereotype. No one wants to buy a computer from a cocky teenager who thinks their questions are stupid and that they’re wasting his time. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There’s no clear call to action.&lt;/strong&gt; I’ve alluded to this a little already, but the most important thing missing from this ad is that there’s absolutely zero payoff. No moral. No happy ending. Nothing to tell the consumer what they should take away and do next. They don’t even explain that these “friendly&amp;quot; Geniuses can be found right by where you live at your local Apple Store. This is a product ad targeted at people who don’t know anything about the product, and Apple fails in the most fundamental way by not telling them anything about it or even where to buy it.
When I was with Microsoft, I saw vapid creative like this get created and published all the time. It wasn’t because people at Microsoft didn’t know what they were doing. There were and there continue to be a lot of extremely talented people at Microsoft.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collateral like this happens when there is no creative vision coming down from senior leaders. When leaders delegate the vision downward, middle managers end up having to make the final call, but in almost all cases they don’t have the power to do so alone. So, they go about securing buy-off from multiple teams, and the result was leadership by committee. Not exactly the Apple way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s been much said about whether Tim Cook can steer the great ship that is Apple into another decade of innovation. While he may still be getting his sea legs, this ad along with other marketing blunders over the past few months make it clear that this is no longer Steve Jobs’ Apple, for better or for worse.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://seanoliver.me/apple-ads&quot;&gt;Why Apple's New Ads Look Like Microsoft Made Them&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;http://seanoliver.me&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on July 30, 2012.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>

</feed>